Guide to the Julio Elizalde Papers [Guía a los escritos de Julio Elizalde], 1973-2007 LATINAMER.2013.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Writings, Undated, II.
  - Writings, Undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - El control de la prensa (Especial para Guerra) [The Control of the Press (Special for Guerra)], 6.; 2 pages
    - Europa: Congreso comunista (Especial para Guerra) [Europe: Communist Congress (Special for Guerra)], 7.; 2 pages
    - La posición de Pekín [Beijing's Position], 8.; 2 pages
    - En defensa del capitalismo (Especial para Guerra) [Discrepancia con Donald H. Rumsfeld (Especial para El Heraldo de Nueva York)], 9.; 2 pages
    - Discrepancia con Donald H. Rumsfeld (Especial para El Heraldo de Nueva York) [Discrepancy with Donald H. Rumsfeld (Special for The Harold of New York)], 10.; 2 pages
    - Brookings Institution (Masoquismo intelectual) [Brookings Institution (Intellectual Masochism)], 11.; 2 pages
    - Un estudio político: Nuevas evidencias, al confirmar la condena a muerte que los hechos han dictado contra el congreso por alta traición, con severidad advierte que es un suicidio colectivo no cambiar de sistema [A Political Study: New Evidence, Confirming the Death Sentence that the Events Have Dictated Against the Congress For Great Treason, With Severity Warns That it is a Collective Suicide to not Change Systems], 12.; 2 pages
    - Rabin en Washington (Décimo séptimo mensaje al National Security Council) [Rabin in Washington (17th Message to the National Security Council)], 13.; 2 pages
    - La lucha es a muerte (Vigésima séptima carta al Departamento de Estado) [The Struggle is Deadly (27th Letter to the Department of State)], 14.; 3 pages
    - Imperio e historia (¿Hay auténticos estadistas en Washington?) [Empire and History (Are There Authentic Statesmen in Washington?)], 15.; 2 pages
    - El imperio en el Medio Oriente (Vigésimo segundo mensaje al National Security Council) [The Empire in the Middle East (22nd Message to the National Security Council)], 16.; 3 pages
    - ¿Está Despertando la Doctrina Monroe? [Is the Monroe Doctrine Awakening?], 17.; 2 pages
    - Desde la cima del drama mundial: Otro escándalo, con fuerza para destruir, diez veces, a la presidencia de los Estados Unidos [At the Heights of World Conflict: Another Scandal, With the Force to Destroy, Ten Times, the Presidency of the United States], 18.; 3 pages
    - Breves observaciones [Brief Observations], 19.; 4 pages
    - Victoria Consumada (Octava carta al Exilio Político) [Victory Accomplished (Eight Letter to the Political Exile)], 20.; 2 pages
    - Elogio de Napoleón Reyes [Praise for Napoleon Reyes], 21.; 3 pages
    - El oso ataca al dragón [The Bear Attacks the Dragon], 22.; 2 pages
    - El caballo de Troya [The Trojan Horse], 23.; 3 pages
    - Delincuencia internacional [International Delinquency], 24.; 2 pages
    - U.S.A.-China: Un enlace vital [U.S.A.-China: Vital Link], 25.; 2 pages
    - ¿Justifica el Congreso su existencia en la segunda mitad del siglo XX? (Especial para El Heraldo de Nueva York) [Is the Existence of the Congress Justified in the Second Half of the 20th Century? (Special for The Harold of New York)], 26.; 2 pages
    - ¿Penetró U.S.A. en el eclipse? (Mensaje al National Security Council) [Did the U.S.A. Enter in the Eclipse? (Message to the National Security Council)], 27.; 2 pages
    - La revolución cultural: Mao Tse Tung (Primero de una serie de tres) [The Cultural Revolution: Mao Tse Tung (First in a Series of Three)], 28.; 2 pages
    - La vida, el arte y la lucha [Life, Art, and the Struggle], 29.; 3 pages
  - Writings, Undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - El viaje a Moscú a la luz de la lucha [The Trip to Moscow in Light of the Struggle], 1.; 3 pages
    - Castro, Cuba y U.S.A. (Segundo en una serie de tres) [Castro, Cuba, and the U.S.A. (Second in a Series of Three)], 2.; 3 pages
    - Drama sobre las aguas [Drama Over Waters], 3.; 3 pages
    - La lucha en el planeta [The Struggle on Earth], 4.; 3 pages
    - La mente de Adolf Hitler (Sexto y final de una serie) [The Mind of Adolf Hitler (Sixth and Final of a Series)], 5.; 3 pages
    - U.S.A.-Alemania: La alianza imprescindible (Especial para Guerra) [U.S.A.-Germany: The Imprescindible Alliance (Special for Guerra)], 6.; 2 pages
    - Derrota norteamericana (Séptimo mensaje al National Security Council) [North American Defeat (Seventh Message to the National Security Council)], 7.; 2 pages
    - Abrazo de dos banderas [Embrace of Two Flags], 8.; 2 pages
    - Meditación de Casandra (Décimo segunda carta al Pentágono) [Reflection of Cassandra (12th Letter to the the Pentagon)], 9.; 2 pages
    - El hemisferio (Un estudio político) [The Hemisphere (A Political Study)], 10.; 3 pages
    - Contactos secretos Israel-U.R.S.S. (Décimo cuarto mensaje al National Security Council) [Secret Communication Israeli-U.R.S.S. (14th Message to the National Security Council)], 11.; 2 pages
    - Maniobras de la tiranía [Maneuvers of the Tyranny], 12.; 3 pages
    - Joyas cinematográficas [Cinematographic Jewels], 13.; 3 pages
    - La Mafia [The Mafia], 14.; 3 pages
    - El panorama y la lucha [The Panorama and the Struggle], 15.; 2 pages
    - Elogio de Giraldo "Niño" Valdés [Praise for Giraldo "Niño" Valdes], 16.; 3 pages
    - En defensa de la C.I.A. [In Defense of the C.I.A.], 17.; 3 pages
    - Ofensiva de la conjura [Offensive of the Conspiracy], 18.; 3 pages
    - La mente de Adolf Hitler (Segundo de una serie de seis) [The Mind of Adolf Hitler (Second in a Series of Six)], 19.; 3 pages
    - Nubes negras en el horizonte (Oncena carta al Pentágono) [Black Clouds in the Horizon (11th Letter to the Pentagon)], 20.; 3 pages
    - Navidades cubanas [Cuban Christmases], 21.; 3 pages
    - Cuba y Francia [Cuba and France], 22.; 2 pages
    - Las relaciones con China (Trigésima primera carta al Departamento de Estado) [Relations with China (31st Letter to the Department of State)], 23.; 2 pages
  - Writings, Undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Saludos y sonrisas [Greetings and Smiles], 1.; 3 pages
    - Victoria a la vista [Victory in Sight], 2.; 3 pages
    - Tiranía y sacrilegio [Tyranny and Sacrilege], 3.; 3 pages
    - Washington-Moscú: La confrontación no puede ser evitada [Washington-Moscow: The Confrontation Cannot Be Avoided], 4.; 3 pages
    - Sangre, terror y azúcar [Blood, Terror and Sugar], 5.; 2 pages
    - La divina locura de Greta Garbo [The Divine Madness of Greta Garbo], 6.; 3 pages
    - Norteamérica en peligro [North America in Danger], 7.; 2 pages
    - Antorcha y reto (Un poema de Pizzi de Porras) [Torch and Challenge (A Poem by Pizzi de Porras)], 8.; 2 pages
    - Makarios, 9.; 2 pages
    - El cuadragésimo aniversario [The 40th Anniversary], 10.; 3 pages
    - Israel, 11.; 2 pages
    - Cuba y el mundo [Cuba and the World], 12.; 3 pages
    - La crisis hemisférica [The Hemispheric Crisis], 13.; 3 pages
    - El mundo íntimo de Bette Davis [The Intimate World of Bette Davis], 14.; 3 pages
    - Castro en Chile [Castro in Chile], 15.; 3 pages
    - La situación mundial [The World Situation], 16.; 3 pages
    - Urgencia de la unión [Urgency of the Union], 17.; 3 pages
    - Hay que proteger a la C.I.A. (Trigésima cuarta carta al Pentágono) [The C.I.A. Must Be Protected (34th Letter to the Pentagon)], 18.; 2 pages
    - Greta Garbo en Paris [Greta Garbo in Paris], 19.; 3 pages
    - Riposta a una insidia [Riposte to a Trap], 20.; 3 pages
    - La rehabilitación de Nixon [The Rehabilitation of Nixon], 21.; 2 pages
    - Evasiones de otoño [Evasions of Autumn], 22.; 3 pages
    - La llamas se expanden [The Flames Expand], 23.; 2 pages
    - El enemigo no duerme [The Enemy Does Not Sleep], 24.; 3 pages
    - Conpiración [Conspiracy], 25.; 2 pages
    - La fuerza en la historia [La fuerza en la historia], 26.; 3 pages
    - U.S.A.: Un dialogo con su destino [U.S.A.: A Dialogue with its Fate], 27.; 4 pages
    - Okinawa [Okinawa], 28.; 3 pages
    - Difamación (Segunda carta al Departamento de Estado) [Defamation (Second Letter to the Department of State)], 29.; 3 pages
    - La lucha mundial (Cuadragésima novena carta al Pentágono) [The World Struggle (49th Letter to the Pentagon)], 30.; 2 pages
    - Thiu Debe Ser Apoyado [Thiu Should Be Supported], 31.; 2 pages
    - Divagaciones [Digressions], 32.; 2 pages
    - Acuarela [Watercolor], 33.; 1 page
  - Writings, Undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Correspondencia al Sr. Manolo García [Correspondence to Mr. Manolo Garcia], 1.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia al Sr. Manolo García Oliva [Correspondence to Mr. Manolo Garcia Oliva], 2.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia al Sr. Santelices [Correspondence to Mr. Santelices], 3.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 4.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 5.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Kiko [Correspondence to Kiko], 6.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 7.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Armando [Correspondence to Armando], 8.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 9.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Lolita [Correspondence to Lolita], 10.; 1 page
    - Respuesta de Elizalde al Sr. Benito López [Response from Elizalde to Mr. Benito Lopez], 11.; 1 page
    - Cuba: Monumento social [Cuba: Social Monument], 12.; 3 pages
    - La nueva nación y la nueva sociedad cubanas: La nación y la sociedad cubana del futuro [The New Cuban Nation and Society: The Cuban Nation and Society of the Future], 13.; 5 pages
    - Diálogo con los muertos [Dialogue with the Dead], 14.; 3 pages
    - La nación y la sociedad cubana del futuro [The Cuban Nation and Society of the Future], 15.; 4 pages
    - La nación y la sociedad cubana del futuro [The Cuban Nation and Society of the Future], 16.; 8 pages
    - Trabajo sobre la publicación de documentos secretos del Pentágono [Work About the Publication of Secret Documents of the Pentagon], 17.; 3 pages
    - Reflexiones [Reflections], 18.; 3 pages
    - Correspondencia [Correspondence], 19.; 1 page
  - Writings, Undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Juan A. Martínez: Un auténtico capitán de industria [Juan A. Martinez: An Authentic Industry Captain], 1.; 1 page
    - Desde la cima del drama mundial: El sionismo, otra vez, evita el hundimiento del estado soviético [At the Heights of World Conflict: Zionism, Again, Avoids the Collapse of the Soviet State], 2.; 1 page
    - Elogio de Osvaldo Farrés [Praise of Osvaldo Farres], 3.; 2 pages
    - Horas decisivas: El paso inmediato es la normalización [Decisive Hours: The Immediate Step is Normalization], 4.; 1 page
    - La hora de la verdad [The Hour of Truth], 5.; 1 page
    - Un mensaje especial específicamente dirigido a Aramco-G. Dynamic-Boeing-M. Douglas [A Special Message Specifically Addressed to Aramco-G. Dynamic-Boeing-M. Douglas], 6.; 1 page
    - Nota [Note], 7.; 1 page
    - Un mensaje a los Servicios de Inteligencia de Japón y la República Popular China [A Message to the Intelligence Services of Japan and the People's' Republic of China], 8.; 1 page
    - Análisis especial #23 [Special Analysis #23], 9.; 3 pages
    - Mensaje especial #7 al Supremo Leadership [Special Message #7 to the Supreme Leadership], 10.; 3 pages
    - Un mensaje muy importante [A Very Important Message], 11.; 1 page
    - Dos notas [Two Notes], 12.; 1 page
    - Mensaje urgente al Leadership: Una sugerencia al Leadership [Urgent Message to the Leadership: A Suggestion to the Leadership], 13.; 1 page
    - Nota #15: Dividida en incisos [Note #15: Divided in Sections], 14.; 1 page
    - Análisis: Una revelación explosiva [Analysis: An Explosive Revelation], 15.; 1 page
    - Memorándum: Ronald Reagan, Taiwán y la lucha mundial [Memorandum: Ronald Reagan, Taiwan, and the World Struggle], 16.; 1 page
    - Mensaje super trascendental #4 al Leadership de U.S. Armed Forces: El F.B.I. y la conspiración contra occidente [Super Transcendental Message #4 to the Leadership of the U.S. Armed Forces: The F.B.I. and the Conspiracy Against the West], 17.; 4 pages
    - Mensajes al Supremo Leadership [Messages to the Supreme Leadership], 18.; 1 page
    - Réplica a Martha Valdés [Duplicate to Martha Valdés], 19.
    - Los crímenes, atrocidades, arbitrariedades de Israel jamás se habían presenciado en las edades moderna y contemporánea [The Crimes, Atrocities, Arbitrariness of Israel Never Could Have Been Seen in Modern and Contemporary Times], 20.; 3 pages
    - Mediación objetiva [Objective Mediation], 21.; 7 pages
    - Drama político en U.S.A. [Political Drama in the U.S.A.], 22.; 7 pages
    - Colección de manuscritos fragmentados [Collection of Fragmented Manuscripts], 23.; 4 pages
  - Writings, Undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Colección de hojas sueltas [Collection of Loose Pages], 1.; 37 pages
- Background, III.
  - Personal documents (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Poemas: "Fidel Castro" y "Batista" [Poems: "Fidel Castro" and "Batista"], 22 de septiembre, 1960 [September 22, 1960]; 1.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Dr. Leopoldo Pio Elizalde. The Journal of Commerce New York [Correpsondence to Dr. Leopoldo Pio Elizalde. The Journal of Commerce New York, 24 de octubre, 1961 [October 24, 1961]; 2.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Julio Elizalde sobre Cuba [Correspondence to Julio Elizalde about Cuba], 20 de noviembre, 1961 [November 20, 1961]; 3.; 1 page
    - Carta escrita por Leopoldo Pio Elizalde sobre Cuba [Letter Written by Leopoldo Pio Elizalde about Cuba], 17 de enero [January 17]; 4.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Dr. Leopoldo Pio Elizalde de Charles Richard Werner, secretario y presidente de la Asociación Americo-Mexicana [Correspondence to Dr. Leopoldo Pio Elizalde de Charles Richard Werner, secretary and president of the Mexican-American Association], 4 de marzo, 1964 [March 4, 1964]; 5.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Julio Elizalde de Fulgencio Rubén Batista [Correspondence to Julio Elizalde from Fulgencio Rubén Batista ], 22 de abril, 1968 [April 22, 1968]; 6.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Julio Elizalde de Fulgencio Rubén Batista [Correspondence to Julio Elizalde from Fulgencio Rubén Batista ], 6 de febrero, 1969 [February 6, 1969]; 7.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Julio Elizalde de Fulgencio Rubén Batista [Correspondence to Julio Elizalde from Fulgencio Rubén Batista ], 13 de febrero, 1969 [February 13, 1969]; 8.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Abel [Correspondence to Abel], 6 de febrero, 1974 [February 6, 1974]; 9.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Julio Elizalde de Paul W. Bateman, Assistente al Presidente Nixon [Correspondence to Julio Elizalde from Paul W. Bateman, Assistant to President Nixon], 10 de julio, 1980 [July 10, 1980]; 10.; 1 page
    - Un enérgico mensaje, Para: Buró Federal de Investigaciones [An energetic message, To: Federal Bureau of Investigations], 8 de octubre, 1984 [October 8, 1984]; 11.; 3 pages
    - Un breve mensaje a la Comisión de la C.I.A. [A Brief Message to the Comission of the C.I.A.], 13 de mayo, 1985 [May 13, 1985]; 12.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia entre Julio Elizalde y Larry R. Strawderman, Coordinador de Información y Privacidad de la C.I.A. Tres cartas [Correspondence between Julio Elizalde and Larry R. Strawderman, Coordinator of Information and Privacy of the C.I.A. Three Letters], 18 de agosto - 19 de septiembre, 1983 [August 18 - September 19, 1983]; 13.; 3 pages
    - Reflexiones, Para: U.S. Armed Forces [Reflections, To: U.S. Armed Forces], 1 de septiembre, 1987 [September 1, 1987]; 14.; 3 pages
    - Análisis: Informacion especial, para atención exclusiva del leadership [Analysis: Special Information, For Exclusive Attention of the Leadership], 22 de mayo, 1988 [May 22, 1988]; 15.; 5 pages
    - Nota #137: Una situación muy explosiva [Note #137: A Very Explosive Situation], 21 de octubre, 1989 [October 21, 1989]; 16.; 3 pages
    - Nota especial: Una intriga, grande y posiblemente muy peligrosa [Special Note: A Large and Possibly Very Dangerous Scheme], 24 de octubre, 1989 [October 24, 1989]; 17.; 3 pages
    - Fotocopia del sobre enviado a Julio Elizalde por Fulgencio Batista [Photocopy of the Envelope Sent to Julio Elizalde from Fulgencio Batista], 18.; 1 page
    - Fotocopia de la signatura de Fulgencio Batista [Photocopy of Fulgencio Batista's Signature], 19.; 1 page
  - Newspaper clippings by Julio Elizalde (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - El movimiento obrero a la vanguardia. El Tiempo [The Workers Movement to the Vanguard. El Tiempo], 6 de marzo, 1969 [March 6, 1969]; 1.; 1 page
    - Ídolos del pasado: Julian "Yuyo" Acosta [Idols of the Past: Julian "Yuyo" Acosta], 2.; 1 page
    - En defensa de U.S.A. [In Defense of the U.S.A.], 3.; 1 page